<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>People &#8211; BlayzSoftwareManagement</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/people/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Blayz Software Management</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 10:42:42 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.4.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2020/06/cropped-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>People &#8211; BlayzSoftwareManagement</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>The ugly side of &#8220;No Surprises&#8221; Management</title>
		<link>/the-ugly-side-of-no-surprises-management/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2020 07:00:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[People]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1250</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I get it&#8230; I think&#8230; &#8220;No Surprises&#8221; management is intended to ensure that people aren&#8217;t hiding bad news from their colleagues (let&#8217;s face it, usually their boss or some other superior) so that we&#8217;re not horribly surprised at the last minute that, for example, our project is 6 months late. Boom! Instant high-functioning team! Everyone &#8230;<p class="read-more"> <a class="" href="/the-ugly-side-of-no-surprises-management/"> <span class="screen-reader-text">The ugly side of &#8220;No Surprises&#8221; Management</span> Read More &#187;</a></p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I get it&#8230; I think&#8230;</p>



<p>&#8220;No Surprises&#8221; management is intended to ensure that people aren&#8217;t hiding bad news from their colleagues (let&#8217;s face it, usually their boss or some other superior) so that we&#8217;re not horribly surprised at the last minute that, for example, our project is 6 months late.</p>



<p>Boom! Instant high-functioning team! Everyone feels safe and surprises never happen&#8230;. Or at least, god help you if they still do happen, because I was very clear that I don&#8217;t like surprises! What don&#8217;t you understand? There isn&#8217;t an article on the whole internet that disagrees&#8230; Welcome to success-ville.</p>



<p>Well&#8230;</p>



<p>I&#8217;m a manager and this is surprising to me (run for cover!) but there isn&#8217;t a single article that I could find in my, admittedly limited searching, that had anything but praise for this management style.</p>



<p>I can tell you, from personal experience, that I think there&#8217;s a whole lot wrong with this management style and I&#8217;d go so far as saying I think it&#8217;s a net negative approach even when given the most generous interpretation. Here&#8217;s why&#8230;</p>



<p><strong>It&#8217;s like slapping a plaster on an amputation</strong></p>



<p>Why would someone in a position of management be implementing No Surprises management in the first place? The fact that this needs to be employed at all speaks volumes about the level of trust, safety and collaboration that is being experienced.</p>



<p>If management are expecting their teams to hide bad news, we have a systemic disfunction. All of your time and attention needs to go into stemming the culture bleed.</p>



<p>The likelihood is that your teams are hiding bad news due to either a highly competitive environment or through fear of being blamed. Implementing No Surprises management simply attempts to relocate the fear from the point where it&#8217;s too late to change anything, to&#8230; just all the time.</p>



<p>Perhaps that fear plaster will stem the bleed for a short time, but how is that patient doing?</p>



<p><strong>It&#8217;s unclear what it means</strong></p>



<p>Under a No Surprises management regime, am I in trouble for making a decision without my manager being involved? What level of surprise are we talking about here?</p>



<p>As with risk, surprise can be a positive as well as a negative. I suppose we&#8217;d all like to hope that positive surprises are not to be banished in our new world order? Perhaps they are though?</p>



<p>I&#8217;ve had the unfortunate experience of management that got very upset when I ran a short meeting proposing a new tool for linking features to tests&#8230; Apparently this session was inside the scope of &#8220;surprise&#8221; and I should have spent several weeks seeding the idea with management first.</p>



<p>In another role, I&#8217;d found out that speaking to someone directly rather than going through my manager also fell under the scope of &#8220;surprise&#8221;.</p>



<p>In short, micro managers love this management style&#8230; and it certainly doesn&#8217;t help that there&#8217;s so little material there to challenge their belief that it&#8217;s good management protocol.</p>



<p><strong>It puts people on edge</strong></p>



<p>Life is a ongoing cascade of surprises, there&#8217;s no pretending that this can be reined in to zero.</p>



<p>Having worked in project management and development, I&#8217;m well aware that surprises aren&#8217;t always predictable. Most situations involve fluctuating risk and uncertainty and you&#8217;ll find yourself blindsided by a turn in the road, putting you in full surprise mode. Whoops! Someone&#8217;s going to be angry, they were very clear that they don&#8217;t want surprises. Bad subordinate! =)</p>



<p>As I alluded to earlier in this article, No Surprises management attempts to resolve the issue of low-safety culture by spreading the fear more evenly across projects.</p>



<p>&#8220;Just don&#8217;t let me experience any surprises, simple.&#8221;</p>



<p>Well&#8230; Now we&#8217;re all in for a bad time.</p>



<p><strong>It smacks of insecurity</strong></p>



<p>I has an undertone of not wanting to be out of the loop about anything. It indicates that you&#8217;re afraid the team are hiding things from you, or doing things behind your back.</p>



<p>I&#8217;m convinced that this style of management is often used by those who feel they need to know every detail of what&#8217;s going on so that, should they be asked, they don&#8217;t feel foolish by having to admit they don&#8217;t know what the cutting edge news is.</p>



<p>Unfortunately, knowing everything in great detail is both not possible and attempting to do so slows everything down. Which brings me nicely on to&#8230;</p>



<p><strong>It creates bottlenecks</strong></p>



<p>Given that we don&#8217;t really know the intricate detail of what our surprise-fearing management classify as surprises worthy of their attention, we suppose that the safe bet is to inform them of everything&#8230; however insignificant it seems at the time.</p>



<p>After all, any insignificant seeming decision or action could end up influencing huge and unacceptable surprise.</p>



<p>The boss is pretty busy though, so we&#8217;d better wait around and not make progress until we find a spot to update them. Or spend time composing a message to inform them rather than spending that time doing something actually productive.</p>



<p><strong>It stifles autonomy</strong></p>



<p>How much to I trust my team to manage their own risk and find an effective way to reach our goals?<br>If the answer is &#8220;barely at all&#8221; then, sure, maybe I suddenly feel the need to make sure I&#8217;m informed of all deviations from the path so that I can dictate how to get back on &#8211; but at this point I have much bigger problems.</p>



<p>If I do trust my team, then my role changes from sheep herder to guide &#8211; I have to accept that this might mean that my team make mistakes, at which point my role might temporarily become politics absorber, but the team are stronger for it.</p>



<p>The fact is that autonomous teams shouldn&#8217;t be bogged down with concerns about how much &#8216;surprise&#8217; I can accept. In a well functioning team, the communication should be such that we don&#8217;t even need to think about what might be considered surprising or not.</p>



<p>Another thing you might find from a well functioning team is that you&#8217;re experiencing more good surprises than bad ones&#8230; Now who doesn&#8217;t like surprises?</p>



<p>Perhaps we could be working with short cycle iterations driven by feedback, then how much surprise can we even create?</p>



<p>In summary, No Surprises management seems like a entry from the Industrial Age playbook (this excellent concept comes from &#8220;Leadership is Language&#8221; by David Marquet, please read it if you haven&#8217;t already) and comes with significant down sides. Perhaps it should be thrown out with the rest of that playbook.</p>



<p>Thanks for reading!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Autonomous teams vs &#8216;resource&#8217; management</title>
		<link>/autonomous-teams-vs-resource-management/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 20:39:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Development]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[People]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1216</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[How often have you heard the phrase &#8220;We don&#8217;t have the resource&#8221; or &#8220;How many resources will it take?&#8221; in software management? Quite apart from the dehumanising nature of the word (should we, in response, say &#8220;that&#8217;s a good question, management resource number 3&#8221;?), people are not automatons who are all equally skilled/motivated coding monkeys &#8230;<p class="read-more"> <a class="" href="/autonomous-teams-vs-resource-management/"> <span class="screen-reader-text">Autonomous teams vs &#8216;resource&#8217; management</span> Read More &#187;</a></p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[		<div data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="1216" class="elementor elementor-1216" data-elementor-settings="[]">
			<div class="elementor-inner">
				<div class="elementor-section-wrap">
							<section class="elementor-element elementor-element-472a2585 elementor-section-boxed elementor-section-height-default elementor-section-height-default elementor-section elementor-top-section" data-id="472a2585" data-element_type="section">
						<div class="elementor-container elementor-column-gap-default">
				<div class="elementor-row">
				<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-985e54 elementor-column elementor-col-100 elementor-top-column" data-id="985e54" data-element_type="column">
			<div class="elementor-column-wrap  elementor-element-populated">
					<div class="elementor-widget-wrap">
				<section class="elementor-element elementor-element-c2599e2 elementor-section-boxed elementor-section-height-default elementor-section-height-default elementor-section elementor-inner-section" data-id="c2599e2" data-element_type="section">
						<div class="elementor-container elementor-column-gap-default">
				<div class="elementor-row">
				<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-4e5130f elementor-column elementor-col-50 elementor-inner-column" data-id="4e5130f" data-element_type="column">
			<div class="elementor-column-wrap  elementor-element-populated">
					<div class="elementor-widget-wrap">
				<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-467c64e elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="467c64e" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
					<div class="elementor-text-editor elementor-clearfix"><p>How often have you heard the phrase &#8220;We don&#8217;t have the resource&#8221; or &#8220;How many resources will it take?&#8221; in software management?</p>
<p>Quite apart from the dehumanising nature of the word (should we, in response, say &#8220;that&#8217;s a good question, management resource number 3&#8221;?), people are not automatons who are all equally skilled/motivated coding monkeys that can be thrown at any problem.</p>
<p>People each have unique skills, ways of working, areas of experience, interests and relationships with others that all matter heavily in terms of getting the best results, or getting anything at all.</p></div>
				</div>
				</div>
						</div>
			</div>
		</div>
				<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-f34f26c elementor-column elementor-col-50 elementor-inner-column" data-id="f34f26c" data-element_type="column">
			<div class="elementor-column-wrap  elementor-element-populated">
					<div class="elementor-widget-wrap">
				<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-7ca8978 elementor-widget elementor-widget-image" data-id="7ca8978" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="image.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
					<div class="elementor-image">
										<img width="848" height="410" src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/06/paper-team.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large" alt="" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2020/06/paper-team.jpg 848w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/06/paper-team-300x145.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/06/paper-team-768x371.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 848px) 100vw, 848px" />											</div>
				</div>
				</div>
						</div>
			</div>
		</div>
						</div>
			</div>
		</section>
				<section class="elementor-element elementor-element-d10c1d3 elementor-section-boxed elementor-section-height-default elementor-section-height-default elementor-section elementor-inner-section" data-id="d10c1d3" data-element_type="section">
						<div class="elementor-container elementor-column-gap-default">
				<div class="elementor-row">
				<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-38d958a elementor-column elementor-col-100 elementor-inner-column" data-id="38d958a" data-element_type="column">
			<div class="elementor-column-wrap  elementor-element-populated">
					<div class="elementor-widget-wrap">
				<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-13b4272 elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="13b4272" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
					<div class="elementor-text-editor elementor-clearfix"><p>This is the challenge and the joy of managing a team, as you get to know each member of the team, you start seeing how they work, what keeps them engaged and effective. In return, engaged and effective people make for an excellent team to manage.<br />This is why it kills me a bit every time I have to grin and bear this idea that it&#8217;s sensible to &#8220;put two resources on this&#8221;. <br />Now, any manager worth their salt will just nod and manage the low priority task in a way that keeps upper management off their back, but certainly isn&#8217;t two full time engineers beavering away on only that task every day.</p>
<p>While we&#8217;re on the subject, Scott Adams, as usual, hits the nail on the head: <a href="https://dilbert.com/strip/1995-09-22">https://dilbert.com/strip/1995-09-22</a></p></div>
				</div>
				</div>
						</div>
			</div>
		</div>
						</div>
			</div>
		</section>
				<section class="elementor-element elementor-element-6cb7aa4 elementor-section-boxed elementor-section-height-default elementor-section-height-default elementor-section elementor-inner-section" data-id="6cb7aa4" data-element_type="section">
						<div class="elementor-container elementor-column-gap-default">
				<div class="elementor-row">
				<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-3b23f43 elementor-column elementor-col-50 elementor-inner-column" data-id="3b23f43" data-element_type="column">
			<div class="elementor-column-wrap  elementor-element-populated">
					<div class="elementor-widget-wrap">
				<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-ca9e6dc elementor-widget elementor-widget-image" data-id="ca9e6dc" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="image.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
					<div class="elementor-image">
										<img width="768" height="377" src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/resource-chart-768x377.png" class="attachment-medium_large size-medium_large" alt="" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/resource-chart-768x377.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/05/resource-chart-300x147.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/05/resource-chart-1024x503.png 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/05/resource-chart-1536x754.png 1536w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/05/resource-chart.png 1743w" sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" />											</div>
				</div>
				</div>
				<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-39fde70 elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="39fde70" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
					<div class="elementor-text-editor elementor-clearfix"><p><span style="color: #999999;"><em>How many times have we seen this before? A resource mountain chart where the total capacity of your team is lower than the estimated work &#8211; everyone mutters in concern and no one does anything about it. No one thinks about whether someone on project 3 can effectively contribute to project 4 or not, it doesn&#8217;t matter, everyone is just a resource!</em></span></p></div>
				</div>
				</div>
						</div>
			</div>
		</div>
				<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-88259fb elementor-column elementor-col-50 elementor-inner-column" data-id="88259fb" data-element_type="column">
			<div class="elementor-column-wrap  elementor-element-populated">
					<div class="elementor-widget-wrap">
				<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-8f68e24 elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="8f68e24" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
					<div class="elementor-text-editor elementor-clearfix"><p>So if we shouldn&#8217;t treat engineers (or anyone else for that matter) as identical &#8216;resources&#8217; to be applied, interchangeably across tasks, how do we know that we&#8217;re making 100% use out of all of our &#8216;resources&#8217; all of the time?</p>
<p>Wouldn&#8217;t we want a big resource mountain chart so that we can ensure that no one is slacking off and that we&#8217;re fully utilising everyone?</p>
<p>No. No we shouldn&#8217;t.</p>
<p>Generating resource mountain charts are a fantastic way to distract your teams from doing valuable work in order to give the <em>illusion</em> of control and comfort that everyone&#8217;s fully utilised. </p></div>
				</div>
				</div>
						</div>
			</div>
		</div>
						</div>
			</div>
		</section>
				<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-4b0a188 elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="4b0a188" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
					<div class="elementor-text-editor elementor-clearfix"><p><!-- wp:image {"id":1245,"width":1052,"height":509,"sizeSlug":"large"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"></figure>
<p><!-- /wp:image --><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>My experience as a technical project manager who prefers to locate and work closely with the technical teams, is that they are almost *never* working on what the mountain chart says they should be. <br />Why? Because the reality on the ground is that priorities change, people are complex, the work is complex and the very idea of detailed predictability around who&#8217;s working on what beyond a few weeks is pure fantasy, especially in larger companies, particularly in software.</p>
<p>So what do I suggest as an alternative?</p>
<p>Would it sound unprofessional to say that we perhaps shouldn&#8217;t fully load everyone with necessary work? It sounds non-intuitive, but it&#8217;s beneficial for several reasons &amp; a subject for another blog. For now, bear with me on this idea.</p>
<p>How about we create cross-skill teams that can manage autonomously? Depending on the number of independent skill sets required for your business, it may be possible to create multiple, similarly capable teams. In the case of businesses with a high number of specialised skills required, teams that can manage specific aspects of your product or service. <br />The key is that these teams need to have all the skills embedded in the team to allow them to complete tasks end to end. This vastly reduces the need for expensive coordination effort across teams when coupled with a modular architecture and decent CI/CD infrastructure.</p>
<p>Once you have your autonomous teams, the input simply becomes a prioritised list of features/stories/business needs that the team can own and deliver by themselves.<br />What are your thoughts? Have you tried this approach? Did it work for you?<br />Worth mentioning that I don&#8217;t claim to have come up with the idea of autonomous teams, I originally heard of the idea from Spotify&#8217;s way-of-working videos. I do find that those I&#8217;ve worked with who really know their stuff do favour this model and I have seen the impact in a couple of roles.<br />Some links: <br /><a href="https://labs.spotify.com/2014/03/27/spotify-engineering-culture-part-1/">https://labs.spotify.com/2014/03/27/spotify-engineering-culture-part-1/</a><br /><a href="https://blog.newrelic.com/culture/autonomous-teams-what-they-are-and-why-you-should-care/">https://blog.newrelic.com/culture/autonomous-teams-what-they-are-and-why-you-should-care/</a><br /><a href="https://www.mindtheproduct.com/2018/02/team-smarter-autonomous-product-teams-work-better/">https://www.mindtheproduct.com/2018/02/team-smarter-autonomous-product-teams-work-better/</a></p>
<p>Thanks for reading!</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p></div>
				</div>
				</div>
						</div>
			</div>
		</div>
						</div>
			</div>
		</section>
						</div>
			</div>
		</div>
		]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Motivation 2.0</title>
		<link>/motivation-2-0/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 20:28:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[People]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1212</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[How are you engaging your team? Are you running a regular appraisal cycle where everyone&#8217;s individual score is totted up and ultimately dictates financial reward (pay increase, bonus, share options) or, on the other side of the scale, performance improvement plans? How are you finding this? Do people who get the financial rewards become more &#8230;<p class="read-more"> <a class="" href="/motivation-2-0/"> <span class="screen-reader-text">Motivation 2.0</span> Read More &#187;</a></p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>How are you engaging your team? Are you running a regular appraisal cycle where everyone&#8217;s individual score is totted up and ultimately dictates financial reward (pay increase, bonus, share options) or, on the other side of the scale, performance improvement plans? </p>



<p>How are you finding this? </p>



<p>Do people who get the financial rewards become more engaged and effective throughout the year? Do those on the performance improvement plans &#8220;pull their socks up&#8221; and become superstars now that they know they&#8217;re not performing to expectations?</p>



<p>I wouldn&#8217;t be at all surprised if the answer is no. I&#8217;ve never seen this approach actually make any difference &amp; the psychology behind this backs me up.<br>The title of this blog is taken from the book &#8220;Drive: The Surprising Truth About What Motivates Us&#8221; by Daniel H Pink. It&#8217;s backed up with scientific studies on the psychology of motivation and problem solving. I highly recommend it.<br>The book talks about the legacy Motivation 1.0 &#8211; this is the &#8216;carrot and stick&#8217; motivation approach that the human race has employed for hundreds of years. It works in certain circumstances, primarily those in which the work is monotonous and just requires effort. It works by manipulating base animal drives like fear and avoidance of pain.<br>However, when you consider modern software development, the work is complex, requires deep thought, high collaboration, fast learning and creative thinking &#8211; this is demonstrably not improved by injecting fear of bad performance, in fact it&#8217;s greatly hindered. It&#8217;s also not improved by higher pay or bonuses &#8211; us humans are very good and getting used to new things very quickly and just raising our expectations to a &#8216;new normal&#8217;.<br>So what does work? Pink identifies the following things:</p>



<p><br><strong>Autonomy</strong><br>There&#8217;s a well established psychological principle that the more say you have over your situation the happier you are. If you try to control things you do not actually have control over, you&#8217;re in for a frustrating time.Giving autonomy can be considered difficult when we necessarily need people to do things that the business needs, not just whatever they feel is important.However, this apparent difficulty is not as problematic as it first appears. I find people do tend to want to work towards a greater goal rather than go off and do some tangential thing. To maximise autonomy without compromising business objectives: avoid things like handing people detailed designs to code up, instead focus on clear objectives and the reasoning behind these objectives &#8211; exactly how the solution is reached on a technical level is what provides autonomy. Developers like to problem solve!Use review cycles and mentoring to minimise the chances of the technical solution going down a problematic road.<br></p>



<p><strong>Mastery</strong><br>People want to be good at their jobs, people want to be looked up to as a mentor, but more than that, there&#8217;s a great deal of satisfaction that comes from understanding a subject at a deep level.Develop mastery in your team by giving them the space to learn &amp; entrusting them with ownership. Avoid dictating how things should be done. Instead, provide guidance and accept that making mistakes is an important part of the learning process.</p>



<p><br><strong>Purpose</strong><br>Why are we doing what we&#8217;re doing? A purpose can be an individual one (e.g. teaching others) or it can be a company one (e.g. “to organize the world&#8217;s information and make it universally accessible and useful.”). This is part of the reason why it&#8217;s so important to have a mission statement that gives employees a wider purpose to what they do.Use 1-2-1s or informal conversations to understand the individuals in your team and help them identify the sort of purpose that motivates them.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
